[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software welcome listeners
will use show of software engineering
radio my name is Johannes and today I
want to talk with three gentleman's on
the other side of the Skype connection
about their book they wrote 20 years ago
which was the book design patterns
elements of reusable object-oriented
software and with me are actually Eric
gamma Richard helm and life Johnson
welcome to the show you three thank you
thank you hi so let's first look a
little bit about what those people did
and so Eric gamma is of course author of
the design pattern book and therefore
member of the so-called Gang of Four he
holds a PhD from the University of
Surrey and this his degree was actually
the foundation for the design pattern
book later on I heard he created j-unit
together with Ken Peck drinking on duty
on Austrian Airlines and also later on
he became a distinguished engineer was a
rational software later IBM rational
where he introduced the java ide and
worked on a collaboration tool called
jess and since 2011 his distinguished
engineer at Microsoft where he works on
Visual Studio so welcome back to the
show
you have already been here in 2007 for
show 81
you talked about everything about your
life up until the point
so next some on the list of the four
officers is Richard helm also author of
the book he holds a PhD from an
informatics from the University of
Melbourne he has been involved in ops
law conference as a committee member
worked for IBM Research and was part of
the team which worked on IBM Watson
but really what have you been doing much
have we worked on patterns and we worked
on software technology Watson was I was
at watson research labs but what was
much much later ok so I misunderstood
the Wikipedia I remember he worked on
contracts protocols kind of yeah being
his face remember so and and they don't
he became a consultant for the DM group
and IBM consulting and then actually he
left the computer industry and today he
is a partner and managing director at
Boston Consulting Group and he also
according to the website of Boston
Consulting is if is a fellow there where
he works on technology and able
transformation of companies and
industries yeah welcome to the show
Richards it's very nice to have you here
lastly we have five johnson and he's
also author of the design pattern book
and he is today research associate
associate at the department of computer
science at the university of illinois at
urbana-champaign his wikipedia article
states he's a pioneer of the Smalltalk
language so he is the person who
contributed all the small talk examples
to the design pattern group he served at
several executive roles at obscure
conference and currently works on a
financial accounting system in group
prove yet MIT efficient also welcome to
the Solar Ralph so
I already said there was the the the
authors of this book have been called
the Gang of Four but we are only three
there's a fourth person John Richard can
you tell us what happened to him so John
was I loved colleague of ours um he
worked with me at IBM Watson when we
first started the book and I remember
many times every morning walking down
the corridor to UM shoot the breeze
about um whatever was on our minds that
day and he worked very closely with all
of us as we put the book together and
I'm very sadly and tragically he um
passed away in 2005 of a brain tumor and
we we miss him dearly and his spirit is
in the book everywhere he did a lot of
work to push us to finish it on time
and worked very very closely with the
publishers Ellison Wesley to do it but
there is lots of John um as all of us in
the book and um I certainly think of him
often as we come across the examples of
patterns and even in the work that I do
nowadays and a lot of the fact that the
book got out is testament to John's hard
perspiration if you like after the
collective inspiration in the last few
months in before we released it to get
it through the quite complex and always
challenging process to UM get it pre
published and printed he actually get
there the memory right is still with us
you opened a book you read one page and
is he kind of I see John so that's
really good right even though he passed
away he's deep in our memory and he
really was the master wordsmith and
passionately till the very end right
squeeze the best words of our initial
word to make it better so that's why
he's so fond in my memory right if I
open on page and I I reach on even so
it's a wrong contribution right don't
put lots of its down in it which is
great so he is kind of with us in spirit
today as well yes yes good maybe maybe
some detail about how we record this
episode before we go into the start so
Alicia is actually sitting in Zurich I'm
sitting in Hamburg so we are in the same
time zone but Richard is in Sydney a
couple of hours before us right in the
morning arrive is in Illinois which is a
couple of hours behind us so he's in the
afternoon we are in the evening and
Richard is in the morning so very
different perspective but still I hope
it's going to be an interesting episode
and I would like to start with like the
very fundamental questions the question
is what is a design pattern at all so I
describe it to people who aren't
computer people I usually say that it's
a catalogue of design techniques my
brother is a woodworker he builds
cabinets and tables and things like that
and he's got a bunch of books which he
bought from somebody else of course I
then describe different woodworking
techniques and every and the books are
divided up into chapters and each one
has a few pages that will usually show a
picture of the finished article notes so
the dovetail corner so it will show some
some article that has that in it but
then it shows how you make it and how
you hold your hands while you're cutting
the wood and it teaches you how to do
that particular technique and one of the
things that we talked about as we were
writing the book was that there's a lot
of techniques you have algorithms data
structures that people write books about
there's a lot of design information
software but just was never documented
it's never cataloged in so Eric came to
me and said do you want to help us with
this book and I said I've never worked
on a catalogue before I think it would
be an interesting project so that was
real what we're trying to do was to help
catalog these design techniques and we
were focusing on object oriented design
techniques it was at the time when
object-oriented was just beginning to be
popular and so a lot of people wanted to
learn object during programming they
were looking for for design information
like this and so it was a good time for
the book can you make an example maybe
of one of the design patents from the
book so people can relate to it a little
bit
each of our favorite one well stretch is
very popular right so you wanna vary
some particular behavior in your systems
or rather than just bake it into your
object you kind of come up with the
structure and we describe in pattern how
to make some behavior pluggable and we
have a format in for doing that and we
describe you variations for doing that
and strategy is about really delegating
some behavior to separate objects so
that you can then plug in a different
object and change the behavior
dynamically in a flexible way sorry
about partitioning behavior using
polymorphism in a way that improves your
design I think around mental it's about
object techniques I think it's about
nice uses of option techniques I would
almost say it has to be cool otherwise
it's not a pattern right so we don't
describe how that nelem to link list but
we describe how to use polymorphism to
get pluggable behavior how to really use
interface the couple objects things like
that so my favorite pattern is a
composite and the composite pattern is
about making it so that you can treat a
group of objects at this as if they're a
single object and you need to have an
interface to find an interface it can
either be the interface of a single
object or an interface of a group of
objects and then you'll have some
classes or maybe just a class which is
this composite class which is able to
have a list or or just keeps it a group
of objects in some way often there'll be
a number of different kinds of composite
classes but they all all those questions
are you thinking of course you have
classes that represent just a single
object there your feature the base and
it's a whole collection it's having the
interface the common interface than
having these composite classes and
having non composite classes all
together that make up the composite
pattern and you see that in a user
interface when you have a window in the
window I have various parts but you can
grab the window and loop the whole
window and all the parts of them don't
move the same time here you're thinking
but just a single object you're
manipulate but there really is a bunch
of them in there's a lot of cases in
programs where you want to do something
like that
hey Richard now peace don't pick
singleton as your favorite
I was just about to which speaks to
which we can talk about later about some
of the patterns which should be voted
out of the book um I think for me um I
always liked observer um because I think
and I've for me and that's well before
we started the book it was really the
how think about the role of composition
in building systems
um as a parm and that's about how you
dynamically construct the throughout the
runtime architecture of systems and make
the various parts um communicate with
one another um
versus what is often the static
structure that appears in other
languages in in the software and for me
that was where I finally I think um got
what what about object-oriented
programming at the time and how to think
differently about systems from a runtime
perspective rather than a purely static
code perspective and that's where you
see some of the aphorisms in the book
about book about say luring plums
favoring things such as composition over
inheritance and this notion of kind of
separating out the concept that varies I
think to me that's before the book but I
still like it um whereas he took one of
the revelations curd and up so it's
interesting because it's one of those
patterns which is was in the small talk
right and yeah in a very simple form it
evolved quite a bit right then which are
we'll listeners how to use interface
delay ate it then later on about data
binding how you bind witches to data and
then it synchronizes using observer and
today no reactive programming how you
can make it easier to deal with all
these events that come along so it's a
very rich one and also you see it in
when in my work today and that's kind of
in within the code but also um in
dealing with companies I deal with that
I in large enterprises how you connect
kind of large enterprise systems across
a large corporates technology landscape
make various paths together and you see
variations of that in the large as
opposed and the system level as opposed
to
within a card level hmm um I just also
make one other observation and I I
actually used when people talk to me
about asking me about design patterns I
use exactly the same example that Ralph
does about kind of woodworking but
actually the history of patterns goes um
back way further than that
um I stumbled in Sydney for many of our
listeners may have been to Sydney there
is a pay a sort of sculpture overlooking
the Sydney Opera House which is in
recognition of um the first governor of
Australia in 1810 to 1821 he was
governing the colony of Australia and
his wife arrived with the book of
patterns about how to build certain
types of neoclassical buildings and I
saw the sculpture and went to the UM the
Museum of Australia actually and asked
the person who was in charge of and
antique books if it was possible to have
a look at the coffee of this tan book
did they have one and they brought one
out with white cotton gloves and laid it
out a special table on a pillow just to
protect the UM the pages of the book and
in there there was it was a book of
patterns of doings and and those
buildings were told particular desire
and problems of size number of families
purpose of buildings highly unsuitable
for Australia I have to add because they
were brought from England and the
climate here and the temperature is
somewhat different but if you even today
walk around sydney you can see examples
of buildings which reflected that
original pattern book from 1810 when can
you kind of an instructor can you
imagine that someone will look at your
book in the future somewhere like that
well I'm always very proud it's 20 years
old and still in print right so let's
let's celebrate that for now I have a
copy here it's only five years old have
you read it I actually did yeah even in
preparation to this I feel that I read
it cover to cover
for the first time I think I think it
would be love befits it is quite
humbling and to see that it's it's still
in print and and people actually but
still buy it I think like all these
sorts of books and there's examples of
pattern books in engineering as well
which was um I've I've seen and
discovered since I think all the
patterns in the book are somewhat
Universal because have we you see them
evolve over time as the technology has
changed in some software engineering and
software technology and you see
different variations of languages and
ways to solve different problems and
Eric just talked about some of them
um but technology does does evolve and
people no doubt find different ways of
solving design problems and what thought
people thought was a terrific idea at
the time people sort of work out later
on that perhaps it wasn't a great idea
and or there are better alternatives and
hence the laughter earlier on about
singleton maybe maybe take a step back
before we go into how it developed I'm
thirty years old so I was 10 when the
book came out and I didn't read it on
the first day so what was the industry
looking when you were actually working
on the book and what triggered you to
write the book
so the industry right it was I think it
was oops the conference was the coolest
thing on earth right you go there and it
was really it was a very cool conference
and at the same time there was a whole
movement on methodologies how you design
object oriented systems so design
methodology is not a trial or process
methodology is not about developing
process the writer books about option to
design and so on it was a lot about
modeling right about how you diagram
these structures how we represent the
models and at least to me no I read lots
of code at that time working on my
thesis right reading small dog we're
writing our own code reading interviews
that John worked on or
I draw and it just kind of missed the
coolness I saw in small talk in the
libraries in code we wrote where how use
objects in this wasn't kept in the
methodologies right I think they just
talked about not the stuff how I think
you can use optional techniques as a
developer so that's why I am i found
this deeper more interesting structures
and what happened then I met preacher
for the first time it looked like that
the same feeling right there is
something here which goes deeper than
just the class hierarchies and coming up
with some representation of persons
and/or accounts whatever right so that
was kind of amazing it was a lot of
focus on design methodologies which will
a bit abstract they didn't capture kind
of for meself yes and self objects
polymorphism what you can do with it and
so you you said you first you Richard
and Alicia were work together in it how
came the other two on board so yeah I
think it's I remember Eric and life
sitting in Zurich actually on receipts
on a hot summer time Lakers of iced tea
right the creation myth is can you
please elaborate on the creation miss
and all the interesting things have some
creation myths right so and our creation
is we drank lots of iced tea I guess
yeah um various beers I recall - um yeah
I think so I think that's where um Eric
and I spoke a lot about exactly the
point he made like actually when because
I was working the interviews at the time
which is John's which came out of John's
PhD thesis which was a class library and
frameworks for user interfaces graphical
editors framework would you need raw at
the time and and what struck me was two
things one was a that John wrote
fantastically fantastic code um it was
really elegant and simple to understand
and read but in that in the software
there there was some terrific design
ideas and that's where and so I was
looking at that and think well it's
exactly it's Eric said
you read the methods and nobody's
talking about this stuff
so Eric and I spoke a lot about this off
the back of trips that I happen to be
Zurich for and there was kind of a
meeting of minds there and then at that
time soon or soon after John came to
work with us at IBM Watson labs I'm in
outside New York and that that meant for
me was actually there was another a
like-minded so nearby who we could talk
about these ideas and then there was and
the sequence is not going to be perfect
here there was a series of workshops
held it oops live in the early 90s which
the guy called Bruce Anderson put
together which was titled and towards an
architecture a software architecture
handbook where though other people were
starting to get glimpses of different
ways of thinking about rather than a
methodology methodologically proach to
software is a alternative ways to kind
of capture what people know how to do
things and so we participated in that
and actually got to know ralph through
that process and then sort of I think
that there was a then there was a kind
of recognition that worth and certainly
the rough expertise experienced in small
talk at that time who loved um very well
respected and recognized and had clearly
a deep expertise at that time I'm still
does about small talk but actually that
was another source of engineering ideas
or design ideas that we thought would be
really helpful to um bring into the idea
of this um book a handbook um and in
those days we wrote this little and all
of us I think still have a copy of it
somewhere in the in our filing cabinets
a twenty page version of the book which
had 20 patterns in it one per page which
we put together as panelized workshops
and I think that was really the germ of
the idea for a potentially this could be
a book and it's of
rooo from that so um you first created a
few workshops on on the book or before
yours like started to read virtually any
pen right I just met there I would say
yeah the workshops were Bruce Anderson's
idea he was pushing them in ahead there
were definitely not patterned workshops
it was what kind of literature does a
Software Architect need it was a much
bigger goal to that and there if there
were two workshops in particular because
first one I had met Eric a little bit
before I had never met Richard I think I
had been in the same room with John that
never talked with him before so at this
we all were supposed to write what we
thought ought to be in the architecture
handbook and to write like a sample
chapter of what we thought should be in
the architecture handbook and I remember
that I was thinking frameworks the
frameworks were an important thing that
ought to be and this kind of handbook so
I wrote something about that but I
remember that that Eric and Richard had
a joint presentation when they got up
and they went through these different
patterns I recognized that all the
patterns they were teaching or that all
the patterns they had were things I was
teaching in my OG current design course
I even gave him a different name or I
didn't even have a name I often would
teach them by example but I knew the
right away she said these are big
dentist where I can teach and so I came
out of that workshop thinking still that
thing more important thing that ought to
be in the architect's handbook but that
these design patterns was a whole
important level of design information
that I hadn't been thinking about this
but that ought to be there so I
recognized it was it like I I didn't I
knew them already but I didn't realize
that I knew that before the other
interesting thing that happened was I
had been visiting Tektronix for a number
of years and knew Kent
from there and I was using one of his I
was even hotter ology was one of the
frameworks he had developed and can just
come back in this case yeah kept back in
Ward Cunningham oh that was a project of
theirs so I believe both of them were
after but we're supposed to at this
workshop we were supposed to work in
small groups and make some sort of
toaster that we present to everybody
else and Kant said to me I want to write
a pattern language for pot draw and I
know you've been using hot draw and I
know that you read Christopher
Alexander's books and that's because he
was twisting my arm to make me read the
books only whoever I would see if he
would tell me I should read them and so
that's right one and I was I'm always
willing to try anything okay so I I
won't say I was I was skeptical I was
definitely not a believer but we sat
down and we spent a couple hours and we
wrote all these and he said for a
demonstration we should teach them to
somebody else so we grabbed norm Cerf
and we explained these patterns that
were like 10 of them to him and then
when it came time to do a demo of our or
do a presentation on their poster what
we did was he said to the audience
describe a graphical program and sort of
a graphical editor you would like to see
built and and someone said how about
this and so we said we have written a
pattern language and we have taught it
to norm curve and he is not going to
design it for you
and so he showed how you used that
better language to design a I don't know
how much she knew about hot draw already
maybe he knew more but it was a great
success and I was so impressed by that
whole experience that breaking something
down into patterns really really can
work and that started me using patterns
and in my own teaching and there was it
really was a year later is that the next
workshop was what when they invited me
to to join it with them and John by that
time John was working with them and I
was the fourth one to join the project
interestingly chums PhD thesis all's
about the drawing framework uni draw
which had also seen what concepts like
hot drying there may be a note for the
listeners I'm like not this time I'm not
jumping in on any term regarding parents
because we kind of assumed you know a
lot about pattern what is a pattern
language if you don't we have older
episodes on design patterns and I'm
going to link them in the show notes but
I want to focus in this episode more
about like the history how it came to
them and how they won't evolved over
time um one thing I'm
interesting interested about because
it's it's no a document it is so we know
kind of how you found each other and it
was based on ice-t s as I know no but
how did this name gang of four came into
place not really sure they I don't know
who did it first but you it's helpful to
have a name for a group and somebody
came up with that name supplying
foot-thick mi it might have been Brian
but it's exact sort of name that Brian
threat would would come up with but I'm
not sure whether he actually did our
first fight anybody know it was that the
the Chinese gang of four was in the news
and so it was the sort of name that
would stick and I liked it because it
was also the name of an English
post-punk band from Leeds that I liked a
lot at that time so that's good good
move but you did you didn't do anything
you didn't do anything like behaving
specific you specifically like a gang
that people started calling you that way
we didn't walk through the oops the
conference with chains and in black
leather suits no that wasn't us no he
saw four guys it wasn't us um did you
when you were writing so you you you had
this earlier dear and then at some point
you decided to turn it into into a book
how did that come about that wasn't
important intermediate step right he
said okay we have all these ideas wanted
to some things I guess a first milestone
was we did a paper for the European
conference on opportunity programming
paper we had written like 70 pages so we
knew it was going to be a book because
there is nothing else you could do with
70 pages we had to extract stuff to make
paper but when we started we weren't
necessarily thinking a book it but by
the time we hit some pages it was
obvious that was where it was going
yeah and I think the process from from
there was that so I was living in New
York at the time and there was a a a
conference running in New York
I think it might have been something
called object world at the time and they
went went to that and spoke to John
Waite at the hotel at where the
conference was I'm running and I think I
handed him a draft of the seven-year-old
pages and said look we're thinking about
this writing this book what do you think
here's what it's roughly about the idea
is kind of handbook software engineer
object-oriented zine and and then John
took that way did a bit of diligence and
spoke to a few people in the industry
who he knew and then shortly thereafter
we met with them again I met with
addison-wesley again and then we signed
the the contract for the book and then
the wheels were set in motion and then
from then I'll know we were never we
have only met once in person and he
wrote it all by email I guess three
thousand emails happened on the way to
the book then three thousand emails
that's a lot yep it was exactly we were
we were in however many different
countries I was in Canada ralpherz in
the US I wasn't arrested
working for Apple telogen and but we
never physically got together we did all
electronically and sent chapters of the
book or patents to each other and had a
weekly development and release cycle if
you like where we um slowly but surely
added each of our thoughts ideas to each
section um made sure that well because
of all of us had clearly different ideas
and inputs and slowly but surely
developed the the book over the next
year scythe I think um to have
eventually been put into production in
actually about this time and so it's
August now in 1994 for actually being
printed to be delivered at UPS the
conference wasn't this this time and
john told us told us the deadline is
kind of August
but like Jude was the original deadline
to earn it okay and and began July so we
had like another month after we thought
the first deadline we didn't has another
month or so before the real deadline and
partly the reason we nowadays they've
even shorten those deadlines but back
then it was a very short deadline
because we were giving them PostScript
is it before PDF to as PostScript and
John produced all the PostScript and was
he was obsessing over every pixel and so
they didn't have to change anything that
he gave them I'm you slate tech right so
okay yeah what's interesting no it was a
lot of evolution kind of inside so we
had fights about how things should go
right it was because he worked different
libraries no I work 80 plus plus B
contri wine and from Switzerland John
was interviews with Richard and others
no standard ever and took us a while to
understand there is no right or wrong
way right so we could argue no that's
how you we need to do it and John was
really quoting interviews and then was
quoting other things and throughout the
small talk way and Richard whatever and
it took us a while to understand there's
no right or wrong there's kind of
variations and trade-offs right and I
think there was a it helped us to get to
peace again when you realize that
there's not right or wrong right it's
not parents are not prescriptive
patterns are about trade-offs you make
and then for me was a deep inside so
that there is no only right way a
pattern can be implemented that many
variations right yeah that's the
richness of patterns what I like today
right and I was look at the history how
they evolves have observer evolve all
the variations right that's what I'm
still I still like patterns even after
20 years right I still seat him
everywhere and yeah I still like them
was it at that time that who you had an
idea about the impact of the burp so did
you want to start a movement or was it
just something you thought we are for
guys and we want you to share this and
we'd probably no one's gonna read it if
we see one thing was interesting so we
were really actually scared what we have
right so and the Richard did wasn't shy
at all he gave it to whoever wanted it
right I guess on the street you were
handing it out Richard right now if
you're scared then I don't know you you
gave everybody has a name in the end
opportunity circle right and got
feedback and you're alright
happy match into something the people
want to read that's kind of Lee we were
really happy that the Eco paper got
accepted that a coop which is a
scientific conference right so did this
have any idea what the not gonna be when
we started and it wasn't like it was all
carefully planned and so that it would
be selling for twenty years it was just
not but we in retrospect we did a lot of
things right one of them was getting a
lot of people to read it we had I set up
an FTP server this is before the World
Wide Web
okay so we had ftp server and a mail
server and people could join and we had
like 500 people on our mailing list and
and when you read the first page is
acknowledgment belong with us the people
who made Carnot's I'm one of those
people were people on the mailing list
who would would make comments and so
every every two weeks I think would put
two patterns out and then we went to
bait them for a week or two so this was
it was by this time it was fairly mature
and but we got a lot of feedback from
people found a lot of things wrong that
we wouldn't have found otherwise so we
were pretty serious about trying to make
it good we're trying to make it then so
we can sell a lot we were just trying to
figure out what was right that was well
why the fun was writing the book was
these arguments that Eric talked about
because we got to learn from it it
wasn't just we're gonna explain to
everybody what we know it was we're
trying to understand why do we see these
patterns everywhere what is it about
them and what's the best way to do it we
were even though there isn't a best way
we were trying to figure out what the
best way was and so so we weren't we
didn't these were things we invented
ourselves so it wasn't like we had a
particular axe to grind me want to force
everybody to think our way we really
we're trying to figure it out that made
a lot of fun and that's what helped make
it be good in the long run hmm okay
let's let's make the two final months so
the book came out at oops learn and
apparently there was a long queue for
getting the book signed linearizing
talks in one of the previous episodes of
this book they're queuing there and
really eager to getting the the four
signatures on effort how did it work
star Femi described as the rock star
feeling of them yeah Kenny can you
describe a little bit the rock star
feeding your head at this moment well
because first of all it was very tight
thing because it was a rush at the end
to get the
the book the beer pub slur for the
opening of the exhibition and so we were
quite nervous and a publisher was
certainly quite nervous and the books
that got there literally were hot off
the press and and so the conference
opened and and they opened the doors and
there was a John Waite the editor said
that he thought there was a fire alarm
was such a rush of people to understand
he gave it to toriel at this Upsala know
we may have done yeah I can't remember
because I meant Ralph you know well I
was well on that particular day you
three started signing before me and so
maybe like it opened at 10:00 and you
were there and I had a tutorial teach
and I couldn't be there till 12:00 it
was something like that by the time I
got there
every book was sold and they were mostly
signed then he had a whole bunch of
people trying to get their fourth
signature because I hadn't been there
but they have all been sold by the time
I know as investor we directed a truck -
yes that's right you know it I it's a
rumor I have right that's well they
redirect on the truck and the local
bookseller who was actually had to stand
um I was trying to get as many copies of
the book it was a local Portland
bookseller which actually ran the stand
so it was the sales were essentially for
that bookshop and they were trying to
get copies from all over the US to um
kind of fulfill the demand could
remember officer on those days there's a
thousand people now it's that big a
conference and I'm the point about being
hot off the presses I also remember was
that if you're lucky enough to get a
book on the first day you will notice
that all the covers have would have
walked slightly because when printing
the books you have to sit let them sit
and be pressed in in stacks so that the
glue hardens properly and they settle
down properly leave them for at least a
day or two so they like mature after
being bound and glued together and the
books were almost still warm and so the
first set of books sold that week
all the colors walk so they're caught
and they have so if you're lucky have
force and four signatures and a warped
color one of the things you had said was
about starting a movement and we really
didn't have any plans for that we were
just trying to write a book we weren't
necessarily looking for bigger ideas
beyond this book there were people who
were particular Kent Beck had been
interested in Christopher Alexander for
a long time and interested in patterns
and a bigger scheme and so he one of the
things he had run a workshop a previous
year I'm not sure where that when that
was exactly was in the summer it was in
Colorado in the Rockies but he had
gotten a number of people in particular
Grady Booch at this place and trying to
convince them of the importance of pens
and some of the people who came were
already pretty interested I think I was
the only one of us the four of us who
was at this but one of the things that
he can't succeeded was in convincing
Grady Booch that patterns were a great
idea
and since our book was the ingredientes
Ida dext year he was going to promote
the idea and since our book was the only
one on the horizon I had come to this
with a graph that I could share the
people that's like in said earlier we
were sharing grass with anybody we could
he basically advertised our book or the
next year for the year before it came
out and there are other people who had
seen drafts who got enthusiastic about
it and so you had a lot of people who
were talking about the book and that
really made it made it take off and it's
really been other people I've been
involved in in organizing conferences on
patterns and I've been happy to push
patterns and a bigger but my interest in
that really happened more after the book
rather than or the book hmm so you you
used to take me today you would call
viral marketing yes we had viral
marketing sort of by accident okay um so
maybe we
talk a little bit about what like how
this movement started after this book
was there what changed in the industry
because of the book what my complaints
about the computer science academic
community
this general was was that there's a lot
of important design information that
never got written down and there wasn't
a good place by a place I mean there
were conferences and when journals there
one places it that wanted that kind of
information so a lot of stuff fell
through the cracks and and I think that
that the patterns having these there's a
number of books that have been told well
ours isn't the only one DARS is the most
prominent of them but this is given a
place and that's one way where it when
people write about more concrete design
information but and there's the Q Khan I
guess that's a website right there's
conferences and they have they have like
architectures you you've always wanted
to know about they have people from
different companies talking about the
architecture their software so there'll
be somebody from Facebook or something
some someplace you've heard of talking
about the architecture of their system I
don't know whether that really is
influenced by patterns but that's the
kind of concrete information that just
the twenty years ago never got out and
now it's very sought-after and companies
are happy to let their people talk about
it and and certainly programmers love to
hear about that actually Richard
produced bonuses timepiece book timeline
slide where he added all had on books in
miniature form copied whatever the book
cover over from from the 80s no
Christopher Alexander kopelyan whatever
he coped and our book and then all the
others was amazing PC of fun alright
going opens up at at what was it in the
90s or ninety year for all curve of the
books no one system design software
architecture analysis that one processes
and I don't forgive you Richard I so I
was look at the slide recently you
stopped the two thousand
for is I think P popstar to reflect more
right that's and use this this form
things like the whole open-source
movement has meant that if you want to
get people to use your software if you
want to grow your community you have to
explain it you have to talk about it and
so you get all new conferences where
people come up and explain what the key
ideas are in their software which they
needed to do that in order to attract
users back in the old days when all
software was commercial software you
didn't have to talk about the internal
system much you bought it at first and
once you bought it then you can take
courses from the vendor on on the
internals but now things are just much
more open and talked about later but
it's not just patents patents were part
of that whole process not the only thing
I think ruff makes a really a really
important point there um we way back
then I'm I think was Brian foot in his
classic way talked about software
archaeology um when we were at the
period in the early nineties I think a
bit for people who are starting out um
you used great software but it's very
very hard to actually understand what
makes it great um you can look it if
you're lucky you get access to the
source code but actually on the whole
the engineering if you like at the core
of many great pieces of software I
recall we used to use Emacs a lot and it
was a great piece of software highly
configurable it was difficult to
understand how it worked and there were
generations before that if you go from
operating systems or compilers um I
think what to Ralph's point what it gave
people was permission to actually
describe the design and the architecture
of software systems which wasn't really
done before because of the commercial
nature of it hence it was closed and
from that build a body of knowledge
about how to design software in the
small if you like which is what design
patterns are really about but also the
much more macro level to some of the
points that Ralph was saying earlier on
about actually
describing the architecture of some of
the software systems that we use all of
this day to actually understand and take
that lessons and learning to take
elsewhere mmm patterns are not only
about see before research was looking
forward what's the next same right and
patterns more look backward right what
what worked and open source gives you
such a wealth of material to look at to
learn from right and I think that really
opened this door and he an actor that I
have now Richard was a researcher at
that point and when he had this his iced
tea drinking party right in the evening
when we separated I said well let's
write a paper in semi to conference I
know rich you were very skeptical
wearing your research hot but it does
even make sense right you might not
remember that you were disappointed
disappoint where we have done something
cool but you have to research hard on
and I think this has changed and we can
set up a little bit that was really good
um maybe maybe ask a more confrontative
question do you think patents have made
software better these days better as
much as we had hoped but they certainly
haven't made it worse to the extent that
people use them again
I know cases where patterns made things
worse you can certainly look at one of
the things that happens is people read
the book and they get excited about
these patterns and they seem to think
they're magic but the more they use the
patterns the better their software is
going to be instead of figuring out
where they should be used and the right
way of using them and how to adapt them
so I've seen some systems that were
really over designed and a lot more
complicated than they need to be because
misusing patterns but that's usually
just a stage it's a young person who is
still learning and it's a stage they're
going through which Oh either they'll
either drop that stage about mature
leaves and immature and overall though
it provides the vocabulary for people to
talk to each other about their designs
and people not too many people anymore
who do blindly follow what design
patterns say the use of vocabulary and
they use the issues that are talked
about so I think
well thinking point you know I'm
patterns are not a measure of goodness
right so more palaces mean more good I
must say for my own experience right has
half pattern helped me now when I used
them myself so I had the opportunity
know when I jumped ship from Java to
dotnet platform to learn C sharp then to
learn old HTML and I must say it really
helped because I looked at the other
system with the understanding of
patterns and it helped me to understand
them much faster and also it's also kind
of I found it helps unhealthy
understanding software much better than
without having had this kind of
framework of patterns with me hmm
in dotnet some argue there are already
like patterns in the language do you
think it is good that parents become
part of the language when it makes them
more productive more expressive what can
you say against that right so imagine
how somebody discuss is abstract class a
pattern right that was really happy to
see that actually the language is
supported directional abstract class
like C++ and and all the other languages
that came after right so it's a good
thing so you don't have to work at the
low level how to emulate the pattern you
can just express it directly yeah we
actually talked about that for the book
should we put abstract class the reason
why we didn't was because almost every
other pattern built on top of abstract
class and if we had decided that
abstract class was a pattern then he
would have had to talk about well this
pattern includes that pattern and we
didn't want to do that we didn't want to
like make an algebra of patterns we
didn't want to get too complicated we
just wanted to talk about the pants
himself so the reason that we didn't
include abstract class as a pattern in
design patterns was because pretty much
every other pattern used it and that but
we also agreed that yeah this is a kind
of a pattern because the languages don't
support it directly but they probably
should have small look at that time
didn't know yet over ice nothing some
ended lipstick method right right but
C++ didn't either I think you Burke
Schultz right oh that's you can well
let's let's not go into this discussion
because C++ right is this far away self
be careful what I say here
point is it in Java and c-sharp is very
clearly supported it's not yet it's not
a pattern it's directly supported by the
language in it people keep you know what
the list of people will argue and say
that all your patterns are directly
supported and condoms for idea help
that's a bit of an exaggeration it's
true that many of them are but not all
of them and even but the point is when
you decide that these patterns are
important then the next thing is how can
I languages support them better
and should we change our languages so
that we can support them better and
maybe we just include them in the
language in some way that's quite
reasonable to do that but on the other
hand what that what it happen is you
know there's a sense of which patterns
are the things that you aren't going to
you need to learn them you're not going
to have them directly in the language or
they're gonna be built on top of your
life there's always going to be
something that's gonna be built on the
language even if the particular patterns
in our book end up being brought into
languages people are just then have
patterns on top of them so the need for
patterns is not going to go away and I
think they really learn object during
and sink you know how to leverage
polymorphism belen this with
responsibilities delegation compensation
I think there I think we made a
contribution to education people think
to leverage objects in this way um when
you look at the the new language is
coming up javascript not necessarily new
but began becoming more more popular a
very functional language also language
like f sharpen and Scala do you think
there are new patterns which should be
discovered for functional languages oh
absolutely and JavaScript now when I
learned kind of JavaScript when I got
deep nature program no it's you look at
Shakespeare you and you find beautiful
patterns like the fluent interface is
how they chain methods how they deal
with managing callbacks right deferred
or promises all the things so I think
yeah I can never stop of syncing of
harvesting patterns for all this code
that are from from elegant code and
JavaScript is a good source know the
libraries for each libraries angular
shows us dependency injection right once
you understand dependency injection is a
pattern you go to angular and you know
oh yeah showed you pen injection that's
what it is right so absolutely
javascript is a rich source of patterns
and
I heard another podcast who was who was
telling that javascript is has to be put
into the straitjackets of packet
patterns to be usable as he went from
with JavaScript is you need to have what
a little bit about before for JavaScript
to make it really use you have to use
some patterns to even get to modules
right how do I do model which
encapsulates and manage the scope of
things right so you have four foot if
use javascript as is you actually need
invent some patterns for how to do
modules how to do classes right and how
to do inheritance because JavaScript
gives you kind of that infrastructure to
do that the nice thing about another
language relating this one which I'm
also using a lot these days typescript
and typescript does exactly what he
taught before it codifies the patterns
you have used for JavaScript into a
language it defines you gives you
modules it gives you interfaces and
gives you how to do classes right so
that's tweaks a nice evolution right
JavaScript you need to use play to make
it using and tab squeezed an example
that then codifies these patterns into a
language and supports it directly so
that's why I have any more pleasant to
program tab script because it don't have
to use these conventions for getting to
modules anymore mmm that's give use many
other interesting things like structural
typing and so on but that's not a topic
maybe now coming back you've mentioned
it a couple of time the evolution of the
observer pattern can somebody describe
me the evolution so what what was the
observer pattern at the beginning and
how did it evolve over swing and angular
and whatnot over the years so observer
start as a as a way to express
dependencies among course can't object
model you control is the most most
popular wound model changes you notify
the view and it refreshes and so on and
it was kind of pretty coarse-grained
right then I think Java libraries they
added the listener mechanism very to
make many more types a FRA you describe
a listener interfaces you get the events
that came in they are all typed edit the
type in ocean to make more flexible yet
listeners then you had the whole new UI
toolkits are based on data binding right
where you bind which is together that he
actually smarty color
if you don't have to deal with sending
this notification itself that's kind of
the level below right that's that's
what's the next step I see it all the
straighter binding is kind of the the
approver is done by the framework
underneath you're ready just the clerk
if you say yeah bind me this widget to
this you mall or whatever right and then
many changes table underneath use
notifications to keep this in sync so
what comes to mind then I guess the last
evolution is hold is a reactive
programming that is about how we can
make it even easier right to use
observer that the events become more
first class right there so even a whole
discussion see deprecated observer in
favor of this reactive programming style
in a very detailed way when the original
observer there was a single update
operation and if you if an observer was
going to observe a particular subject it
would say register itself as dependent
but that subject might change in a
variety of different ways you'd be given
an update operation for each one you
would then end up in your your update
you would have to figure out what kind
of change was it and so it would be a
case statement off of trying to figure
out what had really happened enjoy that
but you could be interested in observing
several different objects and then all
of them would be calling the exact same
update operation on you and so figuring
out which one of these objects that
actually notified it was all possible it
was just sort of complicated but what
happened in the observer pattern is
there's now lots of different
notification interfaces every that were
the list or every listener defines a
different interface and with even within
a single listener interface you'd have a
number of different kind of events that
can occur and so by splitting those
interfaces up into smaller more granular
as you said more granular then you get
you get better you don't have to have
all the case statements over on the side
of the code you're you're writing so you
don't have to just reverse engineer the
detail now the interesting thing is that
both small talk and C++ we're using the
similar type of observer design and Java
I always think of Java is being
halfway in between Smalltalk and C++ and
so you say what was it for small talk it
was good for C++ why didn't the job of
folks stick with that well in fact the
very first version of Java came out with
the observer pattern pretty much in the
in the original way but then they
discovered that was a problem and they
developed a hole listener variant
instead of that and I think one of the
things is if small talk because it was
statically it was dynamically typed it
was easier to reuse this single
mechanism in the C++ world people didn't
actually try to have a single
implementation of observer that he eats
everywhere in every library but some do
its own and partly I think it was it
that Java was both statically typed and
they really were trying to make it be
very reusable and simply no other way
was just too rigid but but it's it was a
sort of thing that that when we wrote
the book we were pleased with what we
did we weren't saying well there's
something wrong here and they're bound
to improve this in the future and it was
I I think not completely to be expected
that it would evolve as much as it did
did this happen was other pivens in
particular well see there what kind of
language mechanism came in that we
didn't have at that time lots of thing
have changed since we wrote design
patterns right he had C++ lady child in
existence so interfaces got it right so
interfaces give you also a way to
express things better that we couldn't
then be wrote it and wrote our exam
interfaces like the composite interface
is very easily it doesn't mess it I
would say that creational patterns we've
been making comments about singleton but
in fact though all the creational
patterns are not used as much as they
were back when we wrote the book because
because of the pendency injection a sort
of an alternative pattern that couples
you know it's sort of a better way of
doing things there's still cases where
the other patterns make sense but they
just make sense a lot less frequently
because because the dependency injection
is often a better way of doing things so
you you mentioned in the beginning so
I'm just
just saying the word of the pattern
single so we added it this was an
example everybody understood right in
C++ how you do singleton have a static
member and whatever right so everybody
got that immediately I think there was a
great way to tell someone you what he
talked about but if you think about it
does have a lot of coolness singleton
right you add something global which is
kind of against objects which are more
about distributing things and not having
a centralized sing which will at some
point hurt you because you want to have
multiple of these things or whatever
right it's awfully designed shortcut to
me is this is singleness of design
shortcut you have a well-known place to
get to another object rather than
reaching to other objects to get to this
space so that's why it often hurts over
time so that's why it's not a my comp
fate of my favorite list of patterns
right so I've it to me it's one of the
things which should be voted off the
island singleton singleton has not been
the problem that it isn't C++ and what
people have used it for in in in small
dark is you try to eliminate global
state and when you can't when you just
can't get rid of it B then then you
manage it and it's a good way of
managing it but the problem is I think
in C++ is a lot of people instead of
using it as a way to manage global state
you can't get rid of they instead use it
as an excuse or something that would
make it okay to have global state that's
about because ones' justification
justification for having almost AC it's
a pattern so it's okay this is a better
global states bad you want to get rid of
it as much as you can and and my rule is
it's very easy to add global state but
it's very hard to take it out so do you
think in retrospective you shouldn't
have put it into the book I I see I love
all the patterns that you have in the
book right so that's for I made peace
with them rewritten and I wrote it in a
way to make it really clear that global
state is bad and this is only what you
do when you can't get rid of it so we
could have written it in a way that
would have made that more clear just we
didn't realize how people were going to
interpret it we didn't realize
people who have taken as a justification
for a global state except you put the
book out there and see what people do
with it no no I think that I mean that
the book was a a collector view of many
people about what was kind of practice
at that point in time but the industry
evolved so we discussed people look in
discover better ways or design or work
out better ways to solve design problems
and the language is evolved and I think
like Eric there's a lot in the patterns
and I recall fondly many arguments
discussions explaining them to people
but they were there a view of the world
at a point in time and the world
industry software engineering the
languages the types of problems that
people are solving have changed and it's
a natural evolution that the relative
importance applicability usefulness of
AA small set of patterns versus others
which have or design techniques which
people have come across in more recent
times and perhaps better choices and so
and some of the ones that we've wrote as
well for saying need to be tuned up
re-evaluated in terms of current and
practice out there something you would
think in particular about well you
mentioned using language mechanisms
right we mentioned using new more modern
languages how to represent that patterns
we didn't include like dependency
injection because they came later all
right so I think the book still teaches
youth opportunites sinking but there are
many things you could do to modernize it
or make it yeah what a nice it probably
so will you will you modernize it or is
that something you want to pass on to
the new generation and do you have
someone in mind to do that we've been
talking about doing it for a long time
yeah we're supposed to be doing the
inviting I think
it's a very difficult question because I
think it's the it it was a product at a
point in time and a group of people I
think combination of the four of us at
Graff John and I at that point in time
was a unique a unique point in time and
it's a will be a challenge I think to
each and every point in time is a unique
time I think it's a challenge to um will
always be a challenge to request it
requires a lot of work it requires a
significant amount of thinking and input
from lots of people and we've talked
about it over many years and we were
talking about it I'm when I fortunate
John passed away and that was a write
loss for us and so the the magic that I
think we had there is gone forever so
we'll see we had discussed an outline
with John Wright this was when we all
met John showed before and he met a
parent we talked about the outline yeah
that was 2005 yeah okay this
the final chance to answer to a question
I should have passed which I forgot to
us well what might be what other
patterns work do we like one of my
favorite patterns books is the one by
Eric Evans domain-driven design and it's
not the name doesn't say patterns you
know so you don't people don't think I
say I'm looking for a pattern spokes I'm
going to go by domain driven design well
Eric getting structured this book around
patterns that was the way he was
thinking it helped him to to control to
figure out what he was going to say and
figure out what needed he said he came
to patterns conferences and and had a
lot of feedback wasn't public went
through her chapter by chapter not all
the chapters with many of his chapters
he took them to parents conferences to
anyway in some sense it's a product of
the parents community a really great
book the topic of the book is I think on
G train programming often gets thought
of too much from a a purely technique
and and programming point of view but
should also but originally we talked
about object-oriented being a model of
the problem as well and and so he
focuses much more as a name says on the
doughnut the problem domain and how do
you make your system be a domain model
as well as being an executed program but
ties into refactoring lots of other
modern ideas I said it's my favorite
books I think what's important to me
when it comes to design patterns there
is much more it's much richer to
committee then just what we have in our
book right so nothing we were lucky to
be kind of the first on but now you want
to really get the full richness there is
much more than just be a veer small
contribution to the whole richness of
the pet and community today but I really
do wish the functional programming
people get their act together and write
books on the patterns of functional
programming does you make this comment
about that there's there's so many
patterns in in that style but it doesn't
it's hard for people to learn it
I hope some people will hear that I
would like to close by asking you so
what are you working on now and where
can people find out more about you
upcoming boots videos blocks upcoming
talk somewhere maybe we see we start
again with Italy
well I ice I still work on tools right
then then I love them and I love to
build them I love to use them so see see
stuff from me in the tool space right
that's what I would say here are you on
Twitter or do you write a blog I'm on
Twitter
I we have a team block right so because
I'm not that I don't have frickin poses
if you have a team block on the stuff
you do right so it's a the project right
now we work on it's kind of what we have
greased a liberty system which will
studio disco we shall sue you online
Monaco right and if you google for that
then you find some of my recent work and
also talks about large-scale JavaScript
all right I will I will link to that in
the show know
yeah which is where can people find out
more about you um and most of my work
he's actually proprietary quite
confidential just to make sure they're
um their company Boston Croton will
basically do my work for um we don't
really talk about what we do but the
work that I'm think spend most of my
time doing nowadays is working with some
of the larger companies in Australia and
around the world and the last few years
I've been spending a fair amount of time
in applying technology to banking which
most people will experience day to day
but also in the mining industry about
how to use technology to automate and
operate mines in Australia quite
differently so think of national NASA
mission controls a way to operate large
mines or those large yellow mining truck
how do we make those run in the mind
without people and more recently I've
been doing some work in the social
services space actually how do I think
about
the the payment of benefits for a
country in different ways to tackle that
problem using technology around payment
digital devices so a little much work in
software engineering world anymore
most of my time working in large
corporates helping them use technology
to solve from the be challenging
industry or corporate problems they've
both um I'm so you might experience in
different parts of the world some of
what I do but unfortunately I can't talk
about them maybe you still love patterns
Richard right I do still have had an
effect well that one of the things which
i think is so we worry a lot in our
company about corporate strategy how do
companies succeed or fail and why do
they succeed or fail and there's some
interesting work on which you can access
it on our awesome Cassandra perspectives
website on what we call value patent
which for different types of industries
and different types of competitive
situations where the industry is either
very static industry doesn't change
what's a lot of dynamism in the industry
um so the difference between operating a
an energy company utility versus a
retailer and what we observe there is
that there are different patterns of
strategy which what we call value
patterns which how those large
corporations can kind of win in their
markets and it looks a lot of like
design patents different ways for the
companies to tackle issues of strategy
how they play in their markets how they
compete to win over the long term and
we've not me but folks in our company
have ripped them down which raises
things so things called value patterns
and you can read a bit about those on um
PSG's website alright and i'm locating
that and put it in the show notes and
live where can people find more about
you and your work well you started off
by saying that I was at the University
of Illinois I actually just retired okay
I'm retired so that I could be working
with a start-up called min efficient
which is a very small at the moment our
goal is to make accounting systems that
accountants can customize and have
complete control over so we want to
build things that are scalable
and fairly it's a quite quite
customizable we're originally working in
the investment area because so back
office systems for hedge funds and
things like that but but the idea is
that you often these small groups are
run off the spreadsheets and I think
that the reason why they like to use
spreadsheets is because they understand
that they can control them so buying
some software package which might do the
right thing or might not do the right
thing but you never know but the problem
with bed sheets is that they're they're
not very scalable and if somebody else
comes in starts changing the spreadsheet
it's hard to know whether they getting
it right it's not very auditable it's
hard to know what changes people have
made to them and so for a real system
you want to have something that where
you know who made changes and you keep a
complete audit trail of what's happened
so anyway we are that sort of the area
that I'm working in I'm not hard to find
I go to conferences and do things so um
are you on Twitter or do you have a blog
I have a Twitter account I don't use it
too much but I have blogged in the past
I sort of find a start up again more but
okay not active right at the moment
thank you for all of your participation
for me it was a very interesting episode
and I was honored to speak with you
three guys goodbye Eric goodbye Richard
and goodbye laughs I honest was fun and
talk to you again in ten years you will
find all those things mentioned in the
show notes I will prepare them for you
we would actually like to have feedback
for our se radio episodes so they get as
good as the design pattern good wars so
if you could write a comment in the
block or write a review on iTunes we're
really looking forward to them tell us
what you liked tell us what you didn't
like them that would be very helpful
in this instance I say goodbye I'm yawns
from
[Music]
thanks for listening to s-see radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise SU radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]